<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Santos Gallegos (Publicaciones sobre experience)</title><link>https://stsewd.dev/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://stsewd.dev/es/categories/experience.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>es</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:stsewd@protonmail.com"&gt;Santos Gallegos&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 24 Jul 2021 23:36:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A tale about security in web applications, or how I helped to save a bank from bankruptcy</title><link>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/a-tale-about-security-in-web-applications/</link><dc:creator>Santos Gallegos</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi friend, today I'm going to tell you a little story.
Some things may look familiar, or even you could feel related to some situations.
I assure you, &lt;strong&gt;it's mere coincidence&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section id="a-new-experience"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A new experience&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tale takes place in Ecuador.
It was during the lockdown that some friends contacted me to help them with a security audit.
They were forming a team (with special abilities?),
and there was missing someone with programming/web skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was a little nervous to say yes,
since I haven't had much experience with security in the field.
But it was comforting to know that my teammates had vast experience in it.
I was excited to learn new things from them, and how the world of security, auditing, and banking works.
Oh, and I would get one of those fancy permits (salvoconducto) to go outside during lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wait, "banking"?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oh, sorry I didn't tell you, the security audit was for a small bank.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="first-flight"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First flight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;em&gt;the day&lt;/em&gt; arrived.
We started with their homepage, and some small web applications.
It didn't take me much time to start finding small security bugs.
And then not so small, but not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; critical either,
mostly things returning too much data or returning data when they shouldn't.
And it was from some old applications, so there wasn't much surprise in there,
and the data exposed wasn't from all their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reporting some of those bugs that seemed important to get fixed soon
we moved on to our next target: &lt;strong&gt;the online banking application&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started with a black box test (no user).
It wasn't long since we started to find minor security bugs.
And we found some indications that the API may not be doing an appropriate check for authorization,
but without a user, it wasn't easy to guess (yet!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What indications?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, most of their APIs required a user ID to be present in the request.
So, instead of relying on some session cookie or authorization token previously validated by the server,
&lt;strong&gt;they were asking the client to explicitly pass the user's ID&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Oh, I see, that smells bad.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="access-granted"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Access granted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After we got tired of guessing what some APIs would do and their parameters,
we created a new user and started our gray box testing.
The first thing we did was to check those precious API requests,
the parameters being sent, cookies, etc.
And then, the test we all were waiting for.
Changing the user from the request to another one...
Bingo! We got access. I mean, &lt;strong&gt;damn, we got access???&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that shocking reveal, we kept digging for more endpoints to test.
The obvious one was to try to transfer money from/to other accounts, but there was a little problem.
An &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/One-time_password"&gt;OTP&lt;/a&gt; was required for each transaction.
So we first made a real transaction to check how the API works...
We realized that the OTP wasn't needed at all! &lt;strong&gt;It was being validated from the client side!&lt;/strong&gt;
So, yes, we were able to transfer money to any account &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; from any account.
The user IDs were all incremental,
which means that you could easily steal money from everyone in the bank.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Damn! THAT IS SHOCKING! Someone could have easily emptied the accounts of everyone!
But it would have been very obvious if it has happened.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or just steal 50 cents from everyone in the bank each month.
Do you really know exactly how much money do you have in your bank account?
Would you even care if only 50 cents were missing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;That's a low and long game to play, but still easy to track.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or you could just buy things, and pay with a wire transfer.
That way the money goes to several people instead of just one.
There are more ways you could exploit this without anyone noticing it, for sure.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="interlude-about-boxes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Interlude - about boxes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, you did a black and gray box tests, is there a white one? and what those colors mean?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The color thing is about how much information and access you have to the application.
In a black box test, you don't know anything about the system internals.
In a gray box test, you have some knowledge of the application, like the architecture,
technologies being used and intern access to the application (like a user!).
And finally the white one, you have access to the source code.
But we didn't do that one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="consequences"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point more than shocked, &lt;strong&gt;I was scare and disappointed&lt;/strong&gt;.
Scare of knowing this vulnerability existed and was &lt;strong&gt;easy to exploit&lt;/strong&gt;.
The money from all the people was in danger, maybe even their lives!
And disappointed to know that this application has been sold to this bank (and others!) for a lot of money,
and the company behind it has been doing so for more than 15 years.
And also, that all these banks have been for many security audits,
and &lt;strong&gt;NO ONE&lt;/strong&gt; found any of the things we reported.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What do you mean with their lives were in danger?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You could disagree with me on this one,
personally I think that a bank is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Safety-critical_system"&gt;SCS&lt;/a&gt;,
Nothing good can happen
if something goes wrong with people's money,
or all their savings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No one found that after several audits? WOW! Why do you think they missed them?
And how the developers missed that!?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sadly. Laziness, inexperience and negligence.
Here people don't like to go very &lt;em&gt;technical&lt;/em&gt;,
but instead go with degrees and certifications ($$$).
And when doing the audit, they only run automated tools
without doing any manual checking, or trust that the apps are secure,
or everyone in the team knows only about networking.
And from the developers side, what can I say?
Most developers here don't know what a unit test is,
or are afraid to say "I'm not qualified to build this, we need someone else".&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="not-surprised"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Not surprised&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say this was &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; shocking,
I mean, I have seen things like this on several apps in my country before,
but seeing this happening in a bank... that's another thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;So, what happened after you reported this?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, the company behind the application negated that the bug existed,
but we provided enough proofs in our report that invalidated all those claims.
And they even charged the bank for fixing those vulnerabilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;WTF? That's unethical.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yeah, but sadly I learned that's how the banking/enterprise world works.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We found more shocking things&lt;/strong&gt;, but I may tell you that in another occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="the-end"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The end&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a developer&lt;/strong&gt;, please always make sure to write tests for you code,
especially if you are dealing with sensitive data.
If you feel you may not have enough experience to work on something,
don't be afraid to say so, and ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are doing a security audit&lt;/strong&gt;,
please bring a diverse team,
or be clear with the client about what things you may not be dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are looking to do a security audit at your company&lt;/strong&gt;,
I may know a great team with experts in different areas that &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://stsewd.dev/es/about"&gt;you could hire&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tale may have been inspired by a real situation,
and some things may have been exaggerated (or maybe not?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/a-tale-about-security-in-web-applications/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2021 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Devsu Code Jam 2019 - solutions and my experience</title><link>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/devsucodejam-2019/</link><dc:creator>Santos Gallegos</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last year I participated in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.devsucodejam.com/"&gt;Devsu Codejam 2019&lt;/a&gt; contest,
which is about solving programming problems.
The first place? A car 🚗.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contest was for all developers from Ecuador,
this is the first time I have heard about this type of contests being organized in Ecuador,
so it caught my attention (well, the car a little too).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="align-center"&gt;
&lt;img alt="/images/devsucodejam-2019/web.png" src="https://stsewd.dev/images/devsucodejam-2019/web.png"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Devsu Codejam front page&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a little of background about myself.
I have participated in some contests about problem solving in the past:
three times in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ieeextreme.org/"&gt;IEEEXtreme programming&lt;/a&gt; (before the university kicked me out),
and a couple on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hackerrank.com/stsewd"&gt;Hackerrank&lt;/a&gt;, so I'm kind of familiar with them.
I stopped participating in these kind of contests for a while,
so this was a good opportunity to get back into the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contest was split into two categories (students and professionals), and it had two rounds.
The first round was online (November 23th), and was around ~4 hours with 16 problems.
The first 50 of each category from the first round could go the second round held in Quito,
the capital of Ecuador (November 30th), this phase was around 3 hours with 10 problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I participated in the professionals category.
And got the 10th place in the first round, and the 7th place in the final round.
What? Did you think I won the car? Sorry friend, I didn't mean to disappoint you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I arrived at Quito the day before the contest,
met some friends and got drunk, and didn't get much sleep.
And the day of the contest my allergies didn't play nice...
so I had a running nose during the whole contest.
And yes, those are silly excuses, but a 7th place isn't bad 😃
(and they gave some prizes to the first 10 of each category).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was my experience, now let's get back to the problems.
I uploaded my solutions from the first round here
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/stsewd/devsucodejam-2019"&gt;https://github.com/stsewd/devsucodejam-2019&lt;/a&gt; and from the final round here &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/stsewd/devsucodejam-2019-final"&gt;https://github.com/stsewd/devsucodejam-2019-final&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't have access to the platform with all the test cases,
so I can't guarantee all the solutions are correct,
but I believe most of them are :).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Note&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I was planning in writting the explanation for all solutions,
but then I realized the posts would be too long to read &lt;em&gt;and write&lt;/em&gt;...
So I'm just linking to my solutions instead,
if you have any questions about one of them let me know,
maybe I'll do another post explaining those solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some final words, I encourage &lt;strong&gt;you&lt;/strong&gt; to keep solving problems in platforms like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.hackerrank.com/"&gt;hackerrank&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://hackerearth.com/"&gt;hackerearth&lt;/a&gt;.
You'll realize how using a different algorithm or data structure will make your programs faster,
how some small optimizations can make a big difference when handling large amounts of data,
start thinking outside the box when solving real-life problems,
and see math as your best friend when solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is another plus,
when solving problems, at the same time you'll be building your portfolio,
and showing your &lt;em&gt;real skills&lt;/em&gt; to the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you want to master a programming language, solving problems is a fun way to do it!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/devsucodejam-2019/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>De guía en Django Girls a pasante en Read the Docs</title><link>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/historia-django-girls-rtd/</link><dc:creator>Santos Gallegos</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Entonces, qué les interesa a las personas acá? ¿Qué te interesa a ti?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¡Graduarme!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Para qué?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Para obtener mi título, por supuesto, todos me van a llamar ingeniera/o.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Para qué quieres eso?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Para tener un trabajo y ganar mucho dinero&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿Para qué?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pues para tener un carro de lujo y una gran casa. Los ingenieros cambiamos el mundo.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entonces ¿Estás estudiando cómo construir grandes cosas para el beneficio de la comunidad?
¿Así como un proyecto de software libre?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;No, eso del software libre no da plata.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Entonces ¿estás aprendiendo cómo programar mejor que nadie para hacer algo grandioso?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;¿¡Programar!? No, eso no hacen los ingenieros.
Los ingenieros no programamos, eso es como ser los albañiles de la ingeniera civil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;section id="hello-world"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;Hello World&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antes de empezar con esta historia,
quisiera contar un poco sobre mi.
Soy de Machala, una pequeña ciudad de Ecuador.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Desde mi infancia siempre tuve cierto interés por la tecnología,
pero mi familia no tenía los recursos para tener un computador o cosas de &lt;em&gt;tecnología de punta&lt;/em&gt;.
Todo eso que me atraía era sólo un sueño, no conocía a nadie más con quién compartir este interés.
En la escuela/colegio tuve un par de clases de computación,
pero a lo mucho nos enseñaron como manejar Word y Excel,
incluso en el último año de colegio nos enseñaron como crearnos una cuenta de Google+
(¡hasta nos hicieron comprar un libro para eso!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mis 16 años, por fin mi familia pudo adquirir un computador,
y luego de unos meses tuve Internet.
Empecé a investigar y leer, me topé con algo que se llama programación y así empezó mi viaje.
Durante todo ese tiempo tenía muchas preguntas, no sabía a quién preguntárselas,
ni qué realmente debía preguntar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luego me tocó ir a la Universidad, en Machala la educación pública no era muy buena,
al terminar el colegio tienes 4 opciones: empezar a trabajar, seguir algún curso/academia
y empezar a trabajar, ir a la universidad de Machala y con suerte conseguir un trabajo,
o viajar para ir a una universidad de las grandes ciudades,
donde podrás tener la oportunidad de ser un profesional reconocido.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No tenía idea de qué carrera seguir,
los últimos años pude explorar el mundo de la computación.
Así que decidí que tenía que seleccionar una carrera relacionada a computadoras.
Ingeniería en sistemas, parecía la mejor opción
(no tenía idea de lo que era, sólo que de alguna manera tenía que ver con computadoras).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Di la prueba de admisión, y pude ingresar a la Universidad de Cuenca.
Ya ahí, en los primeros ciclos seguía sin entender qué era lo que estaba estudiando.
Hasta que en un ciclo me tocó tomar la materia de programación,
donde me enseñaron Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En los siguientes años, nos enseñaron Java, pero a mi me seguía gustando Python.
Empecé a leer diferentes libros relacionados a programación,
seguir proyectos en GitHub, leer artículos de ingenieros de software de grandes empresas.
Hasta que un día empecé a notar algo... los profesores nunca nombraban todas esas cosas tan cooles que leía.
Algo estaba mal... O esas personas que estaban al frente de mi con varios años de educación,
incluso en universidades de otros países estaban equivocadas
o todos esos libros, artículos y proyectos open source eran una mentira.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Con esto pude ver que la mayoría no tenía experiencia real,
lo único que hacían era repetirnos lo que estaba escrito en los libros,
o repetirnos lo que los profesores de ellos les enseñaron,
casi nadie podía enseñarnos de su experiencia propia. Me sentí decepcionado.
No iba a aprender todas esas cosas super cooles que se usaban en grandes proyectos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pero no me dí por vencido, Cuenca se llama así misma ciudad tecnológica,
debía tener empresas muy cooles de las cuales aprender.
Equivocado, luego de ver un par de empresas locales,
pude ver que el desarrollo de software no está tan avanzado en el país.
Y nadie hace nada al respecto, todo lo cool seguía en las grandes ciudades
como Quito (traído gracias a empresas extranjeras) o en otros países.
Me sentí decepcionado, otra vez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="main-py"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;main.py&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No recuerdo exactamente dónde, creo que fue en Facebook.
Vi una publicidad sobre que se iba a hacer un Django Girls en Cuenca.
La mayoría de eventos tecnológicos sólo pasaban en Quito,
y Django Girls, sólo en otros países.
Pero era real, se iba a realizar este evento en Cuenca.
Pero desafortunadamente era tarde para las inscripciones.
Luego de un tiempo vi que en las páginas de Facebook donde anunciaron el Django Girls
estaban anunciando meetups sobre Python, no conocía muy bien la ciudad
y no tenía con quién más ir. Con el tiempo vi que publicaban más eventos, hasta que ya no hubo más.
Ahí se fue mi oportunidad de conocer a otras personas que les apasionara Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Al siguiente año, se anunciaba otro Django Girls, ahí estaba mi oportunidad otra vez.
Esta vez no la iba a dejar pasar, así que me atreví a inscribirme como guía.
Así fue como conocí a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://argentinaenpython.com"&gt;Argentina en Python&lt;/a&gt;
junto a Manuel, Johanna y su fiel amigo herrante (¡no, no fue en una meetup!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ese día me la pasé genial, por fin pude conocer a un &lt;em&gt;programador de verdad&lt;/em&gt;.
Unas semanas después del Django Girls, hubo una reunión post evento.
Estaba muy emocionado, otra vez iba a tener la oportunidad de compartir con estas
personas que buscan descentralizar el conocimiento,
e iba a poder conversar con un programador de verdad nuevamente.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cuando llegué al lugar no había nadie. Pensé que me había equivocado de día/hora.
Pero no, al final llegaron Manuel y Johanna, y nadie más...
No entendía que pasaba ¿Dónde están los demás? ¿Por qué están desperdiciando esta oportunidad?
¿Realmente soy el único que le interesa? Ese día me decepcioné aún más.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En esa reunión pudimos hablar un poco sobre la comunidad y cómo reanimarla.
Así empecé a ayudar un poco a organizar &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.meetup.com/python-ecuador"&gt;meetups&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Así pasaron un par de meetups, nadie más se nos sumaba.
Un día tuvimos éxito, y se nos sumaron 2 personas más (Sebastián y Leonardo).
Y actualmente con ellos seguimos organizando eventos en Cuenca,
y con muchas ganas de contagiar al resto del país.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ya con Manuel veníamos hablando varias veces sobre el desinterés de las personas en la comunidad,
en el auto-aprendizaje, en desarrollar software de la mejor manera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quería ayudar a cambiar eso, dar a conocer que hay un montón por aprender,
y que en la universidad no lo van a enseñar,
nadie más que tu mismo te lo va a hacer.
Hacer que las personas vean que programar si es de ingenieros.
Que es una actividad muy importante y divertida, y por lo tanto debe hacerse bien.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Argentina en Python comparte mi filosofía de descentralizar el conocimiento,
de que no debe ser un impedimento haber nacido en una ciudad pequeña
o no tener dinero para aprender. El conocimiento debe ser libre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Así, un día Manuel me hizo una propuesta muy loca.
Que dejara mi trabajo actual, que trabajara para él, un trato.
Él me pagaba casi la misma cantidad que ganaba actualmente
(¡y un poco más, la verdad!) por unos meses, todo esto de su bolsillo.
Trabajar colaborando en el proyecto &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://readthedocs.org/"&gt;Read the Docs&lt;/a&gt; medio tiempo.
¿Qué? No podía creerlo, ¡me estaba jugando una broma!
O me volví completamente loco y estaba alucinando todo esto.
Dejaría atrás mi trabajo aburrido y empezaría a hacer algo que me gusta,
en conjunto con desarrolladores con mucha experiencia, y por si fuera poco,
estaría ayudando a la comunidad. Espera... ¿Qué ganaba Manuel con esto?
Económicamente, ¡nada! Me dijo que lo hacía porque quería que me de a conocer,
que empiece a mirar más allá, que todo eso que pensamos que es un sueño es posible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Y así lo que me parecía que sólo pasaba en las grandes ciudades, me estaba pasando a mi.
Esos meses que &lt;em&gt;trabajé para Manuel&lt;/em&gt; aprendí mucho, y conocí a varias personas,
y otras personas me conocieron a mi. Así a un mes de terminarse mi trato con Manuel,
me dijo que &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ericholscher.com/"&gt;Eric Holscher&lt;/a&gt;,
el dueño del proyecto Read the Docs me estaba ofreciendo hacer pasantías.
Y luego recibí este email:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="https://stsewd.dev/images/django-girls-rtd/rtd-ssoc.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="/images/django-girls-rtd/rtd-ssoc.png" class="align-center" src="https://stsewd.dev/images/django-girls-rtd/rtd-ssoc.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Espero esto no estarlo alucinando.
Si antes tenía una gran deuda con la comunidad de software libre,
ahora tengo una deuda mucho más grande.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="open-mind-txt-r"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;open('mind.txt',&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;'r+')&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;¿Haber asistido a un Django Girls me llevó a esta oportunidad?
Varias cosas locas pasaron desde ese momento, muchas no tan buenas.
Pero también me trajo nuevos amigos, personas que comparten mi
visión sobre compartir y descentralizar el conocimiento,
ayudar a la comunidad sin buscar ningún interés personal.
Gracias Manuel y Johanna.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El objetivo de este post, no es presumirte sobre mi oportunidad o algo así,
sino para mostrarte que esto es una realidad. Participar en el software libre,
en la comunidad, compartiendo el conocimiento, te abre muchas oportunidades,
conoces a muchas personas, aprendes un montón. Te abre la mente.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
&lt;section id="exit-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;code class="docutils literal"&gt;exit(1)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cool, voy a inscribirme como guía de un Django Girls en la próxima
para hacerme famoso y ganar mucho dinero desde mi casa.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Creo que deberías leer el post nuevamente.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>experience</category><guid>https://stsewd.dev/es/posts/historia-django-girls-rtd/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>